[Music]
over the years it's been generally
accepted that the use of dental floss
has a positive effect removing up to 80%
of
plaque how do we know you can use what's
called a split mouth design where each
person can act as their own control for
example only flossing one quarter of
their mouth they asked study subjects to
stop brushing their lower jaw so that
plaque would build up then they were
randomized to floss half and leave the
other half as the non flossed control
after 3 weeks not only did the flossing
cut plaque about 60% more importantly it
cut signs of gingivitis in half bleeding
on probing and another index of gum
inflammation note though this is
comparing flossing to nothing they
weren't allowed to brush the jaw so yeah
flossing is better than nothing but is
flossing plus brushing better than just
brushing alone the advocacy of floss
hinges in large part on common sense but
Common Sense doesn't go very far as a
form of evidence you don't really know
until you put it to the test what's the
efficacy of dental floss in addition to
a toothbrush
surprisingly only three out of the 11
studies they looked at found a
significant added benefit the anti
flossers were positively giddy comparing
dentists who continued to Advocate
flossing in the face of the data to Flat
earthers Dentistry is a profession in
denial over 80% of people don't floss
regularly it's just hard for the dental
Elite to accept that the great unflossed
masses were right and US doctors were
wrong flossing doesn't work get over
it so you've heard of the tooth fairy is
flossing just some tooth fairy
tale this review was published back in
2008 since then more studies were
published and while the evidence on
additional plaque reduction is weak at
least there's some evidence it helps
with gingivitis which is a primary
reason you want to reduce plaque anyway
why might they have not found stronger
evidence well the trials were of poor
quality and so the conclusions must be
viewed as unreliable so basically we
don't have good evidence either away
because good studies really haven't been
done why not why wouldn't big floss fund
the studies because it appears that all
floss works the same if you compare
unwaxed to woven to shred resistant
floss they all have about the same
plaque removal efficacy which it appears
all such studies found so why would a
floss company fund a study to show
flossing in general is good if they
can't show their product is better
otherwise you might just go by their
competitor
flaws Where Do We Stand today although
technically the evidence for flossing is
weak more importantly the methodology of
the studies examining flossing
Effectiveness are also weak for example
they didn't assess the quality of
people's flossing this for example is
not the way to floss don't ask long
story bottom line the American Dental
Association continues to recommend
brushing and flossing every day
but what's the proper
sequence should you floss before or
after you brush some dentists argue that
flossing should come first because you
stir up the particles and plaque that
the toothbrush can then brush away and
then the fluoride from the toothpaste
might get in there better but others
recommend brushing first thinking that
that would remove the bulk of the
particles first and then the floss could
like floss some of the fluoride from the
residual tooth paste in there you don't
know until you put it to the test the
effect of toothbrushing and flossing
sequence on between tooth plaque
reduction and fluoride retention a
randomized controlled clinical trial
and flossing first one in terms of
getting rid of significantly more plaque
and getting more of the fluoride in
there when we floss after brushing much
of the particles that are being pushed
out by dental floss may stay in place on
our teeth the bottom line is flossing
followed by brushing is
[Music]
preferred